Guide to the Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 1. Pre-Senatorial Career Files, 1953-1980 TJU.2010.01.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 1. Pre-Senatorial Career Files
1953-1980
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Specter, Arlen
TJU.2010.01.01
6.25 Linear Feet 5 records center boxes
The Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group I. Pre-Senatorial Career Files document the professional and personal activities of Specter in the years before his election to the Senate. Most notably, Specter served as the District Attorney of Philadelphia from 1966 to 1974, and worked for the Warren Commission investigating the assassination of President John F. Kennedy from 1963 to 1964. The collection contains correspondence, reports, speeches, publications, ands newsclips.
Custodial History
Material was transferred to the care of Philadelphia University in 2010-2011 from the Federal Records Storage Facilty in Suitland, Maryland, as well as the Senator's Washington, D.C. and Pennsylvania offices. The physical material was transferred to the University of Pittsburgh in 2014, with the exception of selected photographic and memorabilia items that remain at the Arlen Specter Center for Public Service's Roxboro House for display. In 2016, Philadelphia University merged with Thomas Jefferson University, and is now known as Jefferson-East Falls.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Arlen Specter to Philadelphia University in 2010. Philadelphia University and the University of Pittsburgh entered into a partnership to jointly manage the collection in 2013.
Biography
Born in Wichita, Kansas, on February 12, 1930, Arlen Specter came to Pennsylvania to attend the University of Pennsylvania. He married Joan Levy in 1953, and graduated from Yale Law School in 1956. He became assistant district attorney in Philadelphia in 1959. In 1962, Specter was recommended to serve on the Warren Commission, assembled to investigate the assassination of President John F. Kennedy. As part of the Commission, he was responsible for co-authoring the proposal of the "single bullet theory," determining that one bullet struck both President Kennedy and Texas Governor John Connally. Specter ran for Philadelphia district attorney in 1965, switching his Party membership to Republican in order to unseat the incumbent Democrat. He was successful, and served as district attorney from 1966 to 1974.
After an initial failed run for Senator and then for Governor of Pennsylvania, Specter was elected to the U.S. Senate in 1980. He would stay in this position from 1981 to 2011, making him the longest-tenured senator in Pennsylvania's history. During this time, he was a member of a number of Committees: Judiciary (1981-2011; Chair, 2007-2007), Appropriations (1981-2011), Veterans Affairs (1981-2011; Chair, 1997-2001 and 2003-2005), Select Intelligence (1985-1991; 1995-1997; Chair, 1995-1997), Special Aging (1991-1995; 2007-2011), Governmental Affairs (1997-2001; 2003-2005), and Environment and Public Works (2001-2003; 2009-2011).
Though elected as a Republican, Specter was a moderate on many issues, including healthcare reform, immigration, and abortion. He would often cross party lines, such as in voting against the confirmation of President Ronald Reagan's nominee Judge Robert Bork to the Supreme Court in 1987. Specter would again come into the spotlight during a Supreme Court nomination process in 1991, for his cross-examination of Professor Anita Hill regarding her allegations against nominee Clarence Thomas. In 1999, he would vote against the charges brought against President Bill Clinton, giving an answer of "not proven" to reflect his belief that Clinton had not received a fair trial.
As Senator, Specter championed a number of causes and influenced many legislative areas. He was frequently a member of Congressional Delegation trips, particularly to the Middle East, where he would speak out on the cause of freedom from religious persecution and the importance of strong diplomatic relations. He was also a proponent of funding for medical research, including the use of stem cells. He advocated for strict crime laws, particularly for career criminals. His focus on benefitting Pennsylvania could be seen through the pursuit of grant funding opportunities and his attempt to prevent the closure of the Philadelphia Naval Shipyard in the 1990s.
With the worsening of Congressional partisanship in the late 2000s, Specter found himself frequently voting with his Democratic peers. After being one of only three handful of Republicans to vote for the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act in 2009, Specter found himself increasingly marginalized within his party. In April 2009, he returned to the Democratic Party, helping to ensure the passage of the Affordable Care Act. Seeking re-election in 2010, he was defeated in the Democratic primary by Joe Sestak.
Specter's 30-year tenure in the Senate concluded in January 2011. After leaving the Senate, he partnered with Philadelphia University (now Jefferson-East Falls) to establish the Arlen Specter Center for Public Service. In the fall of 2012, Specter, who had previously beaten Hodgkin's lymphoma in 2005 while serving as Chair of the Judiciary Committee, was diagnosed with cancer. He died on October 14, 2012, aged 82.
Scope and Content Notes
The Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 1. Pre-Senatorial Career Files comprises 5 boxes of material documenting the professional and personal activities of Specter in the years before his election to the U.S. Senate. Specific areas of interest in this group are materials related to Specter's time as district attorney in Philadelphia from 1966 to 1974, as well as his work for the Warren Commission from 1963 to 1964. The group contains correspondence, reports, speeches, publications, and newsclips.
Arrangement
The arrangement of Group 1 is alphabetical by topic.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Related Material
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 2. Legislative Files, 1965-2011, TJU.2010.01.02
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 3. Personal, Political and Official Files, 1944-2010, TJU.2010.01.03
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 4. Office Administration Files, 1962-2010, TJU.2010.01.04
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 5. Constituent Services Files, 1976-2007, TJU.2010.01.05
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 6. Public Relations and Media Files, 1972-2010, TJU.2010.01.06
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 7. Campaign Files, 1976-2004, TJU.2010.01.07
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 8. Awards and Memorabilia, 1957-2010, TJU.2010.01.08
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 9. Photographs, 1930-2010, TJU.2010.01.09:
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 10. Electronic Records, 1980-2010, TJU.2010.01.10
Pennsylvania -- Politics and government; Philadelphia (Pa.); Correspondence; Photographs; Newspapers; Speeches; Politicians; Politics; Philadelphia (Pa.). District Attorney's Office; Specter family; Peace Corps (U.S.); University of Pennsylvania; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous); Scott, Hugh; Specter, Arlen; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald)
- Correspondence, A-C, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, C, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, D-H, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, I-M, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, M-O, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, P-S, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, T-Z, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, T-Z, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, A-J, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, K-T, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, January-April 1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, May-August 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, September-December 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, April 1975-December 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, Congressional, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, Robert Kunzig, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Post-election, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, Presidential, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, Hugh Scott, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, Hugh Scott, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, Lillie Specter, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Dechert, Price & Rhoads information for law students, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- District Attorney, Press reports, April-June 1973 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
- District Attorney, Press reports, July-August 1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- District Attorney, Report to the People of Philadelphia, 1966-1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- District Attorney, Report to the People of Philadelphia, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
- District Attorney, Report to the People of Philadelphia, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- European and Israel trip, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- European trip, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
- Honorary degree, Philadelphia College of Textiles and Science, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Israel trip, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- John F. Kennedy assassination, Autopsy artifacts, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- John F. Kennedy assassination, House Select Committee on Assassinations, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- John F. Kennedy assassination, "Johnny, We Hardly Knew Ye", 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- John F. Kennedy assassination, Report of the US Secret Service on the Assassination of President Kennedy, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- John F. Kennedy assassination, Warren Commission aftermath, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- New Jersey bar exam, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
- Newsclips, January-March 1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Newsclips, April-June 1967 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Newsclips, July-August 1967 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Newsclips, September-October 1967 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Newsclips, November-December 1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Newsclips, January-March 1968 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Newsclips, April-September 1968 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Newsclips, October-December 1968 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Richard Nixon impeachment, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Richard Nixon impeachment, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Peace Corps, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
- Peace Corps National Advisory Council, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 4-6)
- Peace Corps trip report, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
- Phone messages, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Planner, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Planner, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Publications, Blueprint for a Better Philadelphia, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Publications, Censorship and Obscenity: A Panel Discussion, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Publications, Corruption in the Courts, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Publications, Criminal Justice Systems drafts, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 15-16)
- Publications, Criminal Justice Systems drafts, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- Publications, Introduction, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Publications, Mapp v. Ohio: Pandora's Problems for the Prosecutor, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Publications, A Microcosm: The Criminal Justice System Collapses, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Publications, The Miranda Rule, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Publications, Outlines, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Publications, A Passion for Freedom, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Publications, Police Guide to Search and Seizure publishing agreement, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Publications, Protecting the Innocent, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Publications, Raw Politics in Philadelphia's Criminal Court, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Publications, Real Criminal Justice- Without a Trial, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Publications, Review of "Conviction: The Determination of Guilt or Innocence Without Trial", 1967 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Publications, Rights and Limitations on Speech and Assembly, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Publications, Summary of the Report on the Investigation of the Magisterial System, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Search and seizure memos, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Search and seizure presentation, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Speeches, Crime, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Speeches, Pennsylvania Bar Institute, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Sunshine laws, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- University of Pennsylvania seminars, 1968-1971 (Box 5, Folder 21-23)
- University of Pennsylvania seminars, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Yale Law School reunion, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 25)